Hi, in the previous video we've seen how we could compute an ARMIT curve and the
ARMIT curve is using two points and two tangents to draw a curve in between and
we started to paste a few of those back-to-back so we could have a spline
automatically drawn between all the points. What we want to do now is
actually having the fact that we can have a bunch of points and have a
a function that goes through those points. So really an interpolation spline without the need
for us to compute that tangent of each point, but to just let the the data itself decide
what the tangent would be. And that's what the cardinal spline is. The cardinal spline basically
takes a bunch of points and compute the tangent for us at each point. So we could use mid-curve
in between. However, it does it. It's basically taking the four specific points. It takes the
point after the point before, draw that line between the two, and that's the the tangent
that we'll be using for that point. And then we have a s factor in front of that tangent,
so we could decide to scale it up and down to give it more importance or less importance
when we draw the curve itself. So I have a function here that is cardinal to omit
with the sFactor, basically takes a bunch of points
and returns a list of points,
tangents, point, tangents of our derivative every time.
So we could pass that to the animate functions we had before.
And if I draw this, basically that's what it gave you.
You could see that, of course,
the first point and the last point,
you don't have any curve coming in or out of it.
That's just because we don't have enough points before
after to compute what the tangent will be for this guy.
But you have that S factor that can decide how big is the tangent.
So if I bring that S to 0, I basically
scaling down completely my tangent.
So I have linear interpolation between all of my points.
And I can go up and go as crazy and having really weird curves
by increasing the tangent size for my function.
Now, it works.
The only issue we have with this kind of system
is that the S factor is not really intuitive to use.
It doesn't represent much except for mathematical purpose.
Usually when we start to work with planes,
it comes from the drawing and the physical world.
So, we tend to want to use something that is more meaningful for the user.
So what we have is a tension parameter instead.
The tension parameters make more sense in the physical world, because imagine you are
trying to draw a spline using, you know, rope and paper.
What you would have to think about is the tension you put inside of your string will
actually decide what type of curve you're drawing.
If you put really hard tensions, you basically have a line and if you let it completely loose,
you will have a nice curve.
So we tend to use tension because it's clearer to use as a concept.
And so what we have is a tension parameters that can go between zero and one.
Zero means zero tension, I have a nice curve.
One being I'm pulling on my string maximum and I have a line basically, a straight line.
So how do you compute that tension?
give you your s factor from the previous algorithm, but what we have is 1 minus my tension divided by
2. And so with a t that goes between 0 and 1, attention that goes between 0 and 1, what you
have is that at 0 you have an s that is equal to 0.5 and at 1 you have an s that is 0. And
And S that is 0.5 actually is a catmull rom spline.
So if you are interested in animations,
you probably have heard of the catmull rom spline.
And basically it's a specific case
and it's a cardinal spline with a S value of 0.5.
That's it.
So what I have now is my function as a cardinal to omit.
Again, work the same way.
So I gave a list of points
and returns a list of points and derivative.
I accept that I pass the tension now directly in
and I compute my S using my tension
and then everything else stays the same.
So if I execute this and I execute my functions,
now I have a function that is drone.
And you can see that with a tension of zero
have smooth functions and with a tension of one
have linear functions.
You might have noticed that now I actually have drone
from the zero up to the last point.
And the way to do this, it's actually
by repeating the first points and repeating the last points
inside of my list.
So you always have something to compute that tangent.
Now, what we've done so far is still
using the AmidCurve functions we had before.
and having a function that goes from cardinal to Hermit
and then use the Hermit to draw the curve itself.
What we can do is try to directly find a mathematical function
that's allowed us to directly render a cardinal spline
without the need to go through the Hermit function.
And to do this, what we will do is basically start
from the Hermit function.
So I've started with the Amid function as what it was,
you know, with the matrix form,
and ask SimPy to compute it,
and I get that formula, the one we have already seen,
with the P1 multiplied by 2T cube and so on,
and then you get the delta, the derivative point one,
derivative point two, and all that kind of stuff.
What I've done is instead of using point zero and point one,
like we had before what I did is that I used 0.1 and 0.2 so I have a curve that is drawn between
0.1 and 0.2 but it's just the same the same formula I have just changed the letter basically
now what I can do is I know how the cardinal spline will actually compute my derivative for 0.1
and my derivative 0.2. So I can use that function here and I can replace the derivative of 0.1
by the actual formula which is the sp2 minus p0 and the same for the derivative 0.2 it's the s
0.3 minus 0.1. And if I again ask it to solve for this and write it as a p0, p1, p2, p3 function,
you could have now a really a p0, p1, p2, and p3 function directly with all the factors here.
and then we don't have the derivative anymore inside of our matrix but what we have is a bunch of s
that represents our curve. So I can now write this again as a matrix and see again it's the same
structures as the matrix for the basic curve, the matrix for the Amid curve, now it's a matrix for
the cardinal spline using directly the s inside of that matrix here. And I can have my cardinal
functions now that directly draw a curve and doesn't go through the step of giving me a list of
mid-spline and that kind of stuff. And if I execute this, now what I can do is of course render
directly that same cardinal spline as the one I had before, except now that I directly compute
the cardinal spline just using the points and not doing the intermediate step.
Now there is one particularity to the cardinal spline and what it is is that it says that at best
a cardinal spline has a C1 continuity and that might be a confusing term but basically what it means
a C0 continuity means your function the continuity inside of a function so a continuous function
is a function where you could always
keep drawing in with one step.
You don't have to lift your pen, basically.
So you don't have discontinuity in your function.
So at the C0, you have, well, for the function itself,
it's continuous.
You could see that with the hard tension, of course,
even the C1 is my first derivative.
I can see not my first derivative now
is completely discontinuous.
And it said that at best you could have a C1 continuity.
So if I go with a really smooth function cardinal spline,
you could see that I have my C1 continuity here.
Actually, my derivative is continuous function also.
But then if I try to get a C2 continuity,
which is the second derivative,
you could see that I don't have continuity
inside of my C2, my second derivative.
What that means is usually it's more important if we if we talk about animation in the sense of I don't know physics and that kind of stuff
if my spline my cardinal spline here is for instance a
Curve that represent the position of my object in time and I want my object to follow that curve
What it means is that a C0 is the position of my object
My first derivative is the speed of my object at every time.
And my second derivative is the acceleration of my object.
And you can see that I have discontinuity inside of my acceleration every time.
It might be visible, it might not be an issue, depending on what you want to do.
Every spline does compute different stuff.
So the Cardinal Spline has at best a C1 continuity, and then we will see in the next video another type of Spline that I can actually give us a C2 continuity, and I'll see you next time.